{
  "lessonId": "lesson15",
  "lessonTitle": "Урок 15",
  "lessonDescription": "TO BE in Present Simple",
  "lessonURL": "bJkSM3g-Tfs",
  "lessonItems": [
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "I am = I'm",
      "startTime": "0:51"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "We, you, they <b>+ are</b> = we're, you're, they're",
      "startTime": "1:09"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "He,she,it <b>+ is</b> = He's,she's,it's",
      "startTime": "1:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я є студент",
      "answer":   "I am a student",
      "startTime": "1:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>clever</b> /ˈklɛvɚ/ розумний",
      "startTime": "1:49"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - розумний студент",
      "answer":   "I am a clever student",
      "startTime": "1:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>hard-working</b> працелюбний",
      "startTime": "2:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - працелюбний",
      "answer":   "I'm hard-working",
      "startTime": "2:12"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>good-looking</b> привабливий",
      "startTime": "2:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - привабливий",
      "answer":   "I'm good-looking",
      "startTime": "2:27"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - англійський студент",
      "answer":   "You are an English student",
      "startTime": "2:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>creative</b> /kɹiˈeɪtɪv/ творчий",
      "startTime": "2:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - творчий англійський студент",
      "answer":   "You are a creative English student",
      "startTime": "2:55"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - чудова людина",
      "answer":   "You're a perfect person",
      "startTime": "3:03"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>great</b> /ɡɹeɪt/ класний, відмінний",
      "startTime": "3:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - класна команда",
      "answer":   "We are a great team",
      "startTime": "3:12"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми є тут",
      "answer":   "We are here",
      "startTime": "3:19"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>free</b> /fɹiː/ вільний",
      "startTime": "3:26"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми є вільні",
      "answer":   [
        "We're free",
        "We are free"
      ],
      "startTime": "3:32"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони є вдома",
      "answer":   "They are at home",
      "startTime": "4:19"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>hungry</b> /ˈhʌŋ.ɡɹi/ голодний",
      "startTime": "4:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони є голодні",
      "answer":   "They are hungry",
      "startTime": "4:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>thirsty</b> /ˈθɜː(ɹ)st.i/ спраглий",
      "startTime": "4:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони є спраглі",
      "answer":   [
        "They are thirsty",
        "They're thirsty"
      ],
      "startTime": "4:59"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він є позитивний",
      "answer":   "He is positive",
      "startTime": "5:05"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>strong</b> /stɹɔŋ/ сильний",
      "startTime": "5:12"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він є сильний",
      "answer":   "He is strong",
      "startTime": "5:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - працелюбний",
      "answer":   "He's hard-working",
      "startTime": "5:26"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - розумна",
      "answer":   "She is clever",
      "startTime": "5:32"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>pretty</b> /ˈpɹɪti/ гарний, милий",
      "startTime": "5:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - гарненька",
      "answer":   "She is pretty",
      "startTime": "5:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - творча",
      "answer":   "She's creative",
      "startTime": "5:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно - маленьке",
      "answer":   "It is little",
      "startTime": "5:59"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>fluffy</b> /flʌfi/ пухнастий",
      "startTime": "6:30"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно - пухнасте",
      "answer":   "It is fluffy",
      "startTime": "6:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно - на дереві",
      "answer":   "It's in a tree",
      "startTime": "6:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>station</b> /ˈsteɪʃən/ станція",
      "startTime": "6:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - на станції",
      "answer":   "I am at the station",
      "startTime": "7:59"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>at the table</b> за столом",
      "startTime": "7:15"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - за столом",
      "answer":   "We are at the table",
      "startTime": "7:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Йому - двадцять шість",
      "answer":   "He is twenty-six",
      "startTime": "7:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>tired</b> /taɪəd/ втомлений",
      "startTime": "7:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - втомлені",
      "answer":   "They are tired",
      "startTime": "7:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>tourist</b> /ˈtʊəɹɪst/ турист",
      "startTime": "7:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - турист",
      "answer":   "He is a tourist",
      "startTime": "7:54"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - із братом",
      "answer":   "She is with a brother",
      "startTime": "8:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>scientist</b> /ˈsaɪən.tɪst/ вчений, науковець",
      "startTime": "8:13"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - вчений",
      "answer":   "You are a scientist",
      "startTime": "8:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - квиток",
      "answer":   "It is a ticket",
      "startTime": "8:26"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - гарний чоловік",
      "answer":   "He is a good husband",
      "startTime": "10:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>driver</b> /ˈdɹaɪ.və(ɹ)/ водій",
      "startTime": "10:30"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - гарний водій",
      "answer":   "He's a good driver",
      "startTime": "10:31"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - приваблива жінка",
      "answer":   "She is a pretty woman",
      "startTime": "10:37"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>nice</b> /naɪs/ гарний, привабливий",
      "startTime": "10:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - гарна дружина",
      "answer":   "She's a nice wife",
      "startTime": "10:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>writer</b> /ˈɹaɪ.tə(ɹ)/ письменник",
      "startTime": "11:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - гарний письменник",
      "answer":   "I am a good writer",
      "startTime": "11:14"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - гарний у викладанні",
      "answer":   "I'm good at teaching",
      "startTime": "11:20"
    },
    
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>to be good at</b> бути гарним у чомусь",
      "startTime": "11:26"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - гарні друзі",
      "answer":   "We are good friends",
      "startTime": "11:50"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>to be at the [seaside]</b> бути біля [моря]",
      "startTime": "12:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - біля моря",
      "answer":   "We are at the seaside",
      "startTime": "12:13"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>success</b> /səkˈsɛs/ успіх",
      "startTime": "12:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - успіх",
      "answer":   "It is success",
      "startTime": "12:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>animal</b> /ˈænɪməl/ тварина",
      "startTime": "12:41"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - тварина",
      "answer":   "It's an animal",
      "startTime": "12:42"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - гарні люди",
      "answer":   "They are good people",
      "startTime": "13:13"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>role-models</b> зразок для наслідування",
      "startTime": "13:27"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - зразки для наслідування",
      "answer":   "They are role-models",
      "startTime": "13:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>better</b> /ˈbɛtə/ кращий<br/><b>good / better / the best</b> добрий, кращий, найкращий",
      "startTime": "13:51"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - кращий,ніж вчора",
      "answer":   "You are better than yesterday",
      "startTime": "14:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>than</b> /ðæn/, /ðɛn/ ніж",
      "startTime": "14:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>professional</b> /pɹəˈfɛʃənəl/ професіонал",
      "startTime": "14:22"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - великий професіонал",
      "answer":   "She's a great professional",
      "startTime": "14:24"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>outside</b> /ˈaʊtsaɪd/ зовні, на вулиці",
      "startTime": "14:54"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно є надворі",
      "answer":   [
        "It's outside",
        "It is outside"
      ],
      "startTime": "15:03"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>inside</b> /ɪnˈsaɪd/ всередені",
      "startTime": "15:14"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Ця) тварина - у (всередині) будинку",
      "answer":   "The animal is inside the house",
      "startTime": "15:33"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - мої сусіди",
      "answer":   "They are my neighbours",
      "startTime": "15:42"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - у ресторані",
      "answer":   "You are in a restaurant",
      "startTime": "15:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>language</b> /ˈlæŋɡwɪd͡ʒ/ мова",
      "startTime": "13:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - англійська мова",
      "answer":   [
        "It's the English language",
        "It is the English language",
      ],
      "startTime": "16:44"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - в університеті",
      "answer":   "We are at a university",
      "startTime": "16:51"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він - там",
      "answer":   "He is there",
      "startTime": "16:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти - тут",
      "answer":   "You are here",
      "startTime": "17:03"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони - на Кларк Стріт (Clark Street)",
      "answer":   "They are in Clark Street",
      "startTime": "17:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>photographer</b> /fəˈtɒɡɹəfə/ фотограф",
      "startTime": "17:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона - професійний фотограф",
      "answer":   "She is a professional photographer",
      "startTime": "17:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>news</b> /njuːz/ новини. 'Новини' вживаємо лише в однині",
      "startTime": "17:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це - новини",
      "answer":   [
        "It is news"
        "It's news"
      ],
      "startTime": "18:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>twin</b> /twɪn/ близнюк",
      "startTime": "18:48"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми - близнята",
      "answer":   "We are twins",
      "startTime": "18:54"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я - гарний у спілкуванні",
      "answer":   "I'm good at communication",
      "startTime": "19:01"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>proud</b> /pɹaʊd/ пишатися",
      "startTime": "19:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я пишаюся тобою",
      "answer":   "I'm proud of you",
      "startTime": "19:17"
    }
  ]
}
